Guide to the University of Pittsburgh Division of the Natural Sciences Office Files, 1956-1972 UA.90.4.2
ULS Archives & Special Collections
- Auxiliary Enterprises, 1958-1959 (Box 10, Folder 85)
  Bookstore survey to determine how it could better serve the University Professional center facilities in Bruce Hall; bookstore textbook supply catalog, Winter 1960; invitation to new Book Center open house, March 8, 1960; graph showing peak period of service in cafeteria; Book Store News, volume 2, number 1, April 1960.
- Auxiliary Enterprises, 1960-1967 (Box 10, Folder 86)
- Awards, 1966-1967 (Box 10, Folder 87)
  John Scott Medal Award and Nobel Prize.
- Religion (Box 10, Folder 88)
  Correspondence from Chaplain Luccock; announcements of faculty seminars; "And Crown Thy Good With Brotherhood" publication of University of Pittsburgh Student Council of Religious Organizations; Dr. Lauffer turns down chairmanship of Board of Religion.
- Religion (Box 10, Folder 89)
  "The program in Religion at the University of Pittsburgh" paper; correspondence about a Department of Religion; brochures from State University of Iowa about School of Religion.
- Board of Trustees, 1965-1967 (Box 10, Folder 90)
  Correspondence about prospective members of the Board; Physical Plant and Site Development Committee meeting minutes, December 7, 1965; retirement remarks made by Gwilym A. Price, January 10, 1967.
- Board of Visitors, 1959-1964 (Box 10, Folder 91)
- Buhl Planetarium, 1958-1967 (Box 11, Folder 92)
  Outline of the science program; Dean Lauffer as judge of School Science Experts Quiz broadcasts; sample publications.
- Business Affairs, 1960-1963 (Box 11, Folder 93)
  Correspondence on procedures for processing requisitions; consultation with University attorneys; "Schedule of Student Charges," January and August 1962; faculty benefits compared 1957 and 1962; new school, Division and Department Code Books, May 1964.
- Business Affairs (see also Financial Affairs), 1963-1965 (Box 11, Folder 94)
  Student charges and name change, March 10, 1965.
- Calendar - Special Events, 1959-1967 (Box 11, Folder 95)
- Carnegie Institute of Technology, 1962-1967 (Box 11, Folder 96)
  Correspondence on relations with their faculty; Dean Halliday to Dean Teare about students attending graduate courses at either institution; Dr. Stever from MIT becomes CIT president; "Memorandum of Understanding" between CIT and University of Pittsburgh on cooperative arrangements; clippings on merger of CIT and Mellon Institute.
- Center for Advanced Study, 1962-1963 (Box 11, Folder 97)
  Preliminary draft of a proposal for a Center in the Division of Natural Sciences and information on a similar center at Berkeley called Miller Institute.
- Chancellor Search - Correspondence, 1965-1966 (Box 11, Folder 98)
- Cluster Organizations Policy Paper, 1964-1965 (Box 11, Folder 99)
- College of Arts and Sciences, 1964-1965 (Box 11, Folder 100)
- Colloquia - Life Science Series, 1966-1967 (Box 11, Folder 101)
- Commencement, 1956-1961 (Box 11, Folder 102)
  Commencement program with Dr. Lauffer's speech presenting Gaylord P. Harnwell with honorary Doctor of Law degree, 1957; correspondence on commencement instructions; correspondence on Dr. Werner Von Braun as an honorary degree recipient and copy of Dr. Lauffer's presentation speech, 1958; correspondence about Dr. Enrico Bompiani, Dr. Eugene P. Wigner and Dr. Samuel A. Goudsmit as possible candidates for an honorary degree; student representatives for commencement, 1959; Dr. Lauffer's commencement notes; correspondence and memos, 1961.
- Commencement, 1961-1967 (Box 11, Folder 103)
  Correspondence about alumni seminars to be held during commencement week; honorary degree presentation speech to Dr. Wendell Meredith Stanley; Dean's commencement notes, 1962; memos on arrangements; honorary degree candidates, 1963; honorary degree presentation speech to Harold Clayton Urey; Dr. Kurtzman's commencement remarks, 1967.
- Committees, 1958-1961 (Box 12, Folder 104)
  Board Committee on Physical Plant and Site Development; committee for DNS Bulletin; University Advisory Committee on Teacher Education; Committee on the Andrew Mellon Fellowships; Radiation Safety Committee (includes copy of the committee's publication "Regulations Regarding the Safe Use of Sources of Ionizing Radiation," 1960).
- Committees, 1961-1966 (Box 12, Folder 105)
  U.S. Government General Medical Research Program, Max Lauffer a member of the Project Committee; Radiation Safety Committee (includes "Regulations Regarding the Safe Use of Sources of Ionizing Radiation," 1965); open letter committee on the Nuclear Test Ban Negotiations; committee on University Environmental Health and Safety.
- Committees - Dean's Advisory Committee on Faculty Development for DNS, 1960-1965 (Box 12, Folder 106)
  Correspondence on appointment to membership; minutes and notices of meetings; Faculty Development Program; special committee reports and minutes.
- Committees - Faculty Policy, 1958-1965 (Box 12, Folder 107)
  Correspondence, memos, and "Draft Report of Joint Committee on Faculty Participation in Policy Making."
- Committees - Bicentennial Committee, 1956-1959 (Box 12, Folder 108)
  Correspondence; "It's Everybody's Bicentennial!" pamphlet; minutes of meetings.
- Commonwealth of Pennsylvania, 1965-1968 (Box 12, Folder 109)
  PENNTAP Proposal; "Report to the Special Task Force of the Appropriations Committee and the Ways and Means Committee of the House of Representatives Commonwealth of Pennsylvania" by the University of Pittsburgh, April 4, 1967; telephone request for applying State appropriation formula.
- Community Colleges, 1965-1967 (Box 12, Folder 110)
  Butler Community College; Community College of Allegheny County; loyalty oath taken by David Halliday as a member of the Board of Trustees and letter from Dr. Halliday to President Kermit Morrissey on membership on the Board with biographical data attached; correspondence about the community college.
- Companies, 1958-1964 (Box 12, Folder 111)
  Correspondence about equipment, draperies for Langley, catalog distribution, demonstrations, carpet estimates.
- Computation and Data Processing Center, 1958-1964 (Box 12, Folder 112)
  Statistical programs available; list of books, papers and manuals in library, November 1, 1959; installation and celebration of $1,250,000 IBM 7070 computer; correspondence on uses of the computer; space for the IBM 7090 system; correspondence on the IBM 7090; possible Pitt-Carnegie Tech collaboration in computing; computer usage problem.
- Computation and Data Processing Center, 1964-1966 (Box 13, Folder 113)
  Correspondence on relationship of the DNS to the Computer and Data Processing Center; computer usage of 7070 and 7090; complaints about errors and hours; draft "Proposal to Establish a Remote Computing Facility in the Department of Psychology"; change of name to Computer Center, June 16, 1966; search committee for director.
- Computer Center, 1966-1967 (Box 13, Folder 114)
  Computer usage and correspondence about Computer Center Interaction Committee.
- Computer Science, 1961-1967 (Box 13, Folder 115)
  Computer Science proposal correspondence; courses in computer science; CIT establishes Department of Computer Science; applicant for head of computer science; "Proposed Program for the Master of Science Degree in Computer Science" paper.
- Conference Participation, 1958-1967 (Box 13, Folder 116)
- Conflict of Interest, 1965-1966 (Box 13, Folder 117)
  "Policy to Prevent Conflict of Interest in Government Sponsored Research at the University of Pittsburgh" paper and correspondence about conflict of interest.
- Consulting, 1956-1967 (Box 13, Folder 118)
  Letters requesting permission and summary sheets of activities by department.
- Council of Deans, 1958-1965 (Box 13, Folder 119)
- Course Offerings, 1962-1963 (Box 13, Folder 120)
  Analysis of frequency of courses offered by DNS, Division of Social Sciences, Division of Humanities, and academic disciplines.
- Course Offerings, 1964-1965 (Box 13, Folder 121)
  Listing by trimester and department Astronomy, Biology, Biophysics, Chemistry, Earth and Planetary Sciences, Math, Physics, Psychology.
- Course Offerings, 1965-1966 (Box 14, Folder 122)
- Course Offerings, 1966-1967 (Box 14, Folder 123)
- Course Offerings, 1967-1968 (Box 15, Folder 124)
- Crisis, 1964-1967 (Box 15, Folder 125)
  Fact book with QA on title; DNS average salaries by department; reimbursable salary tables; questionnaire for Committee on Master Plan for Higher Education; photocopy of article in Science "Pittsburgh: The Rocky Road to Academic Excellence" Parts I-III; Pennsylvania House Bill No.2 which defines the new status for the University and No.120 which is the University appropriation act, 1966.
- Crystallography (Box 15, Folder 126)
  Correspondence regarding the x-ray crystallography lab as an interdepartmental unit; "Teaching and Research in X-Ray Crystallography 1953-1958" paper; course announcement, Summer 1959; computer use; list of reprints and preprints; "Research and Teaching in X-Ray Crystallography" (a history and list of publications); proposal that Dr. B.M. Cramen be made full member of graduate faculty; correspondence about interdisciplinary Ph.D. program in Crystallography; notes on re-organization of Crystallography Lab; correspondence about Crystallography Lab.
- Crystallography Lab, 1963-1968 (Box 15, Folder 127)
  Correspondence on computer problems; publication list; Ph.D. program in Crystallography; the Crystallography Laboratory, 1965; renovation in Thaw Hall; Crystallography Lab policy statement; extension of computation facilities requested by Dr. Jeffrey; Honorarium for Dr. Hanic; article in Physics Today on Crystallography Lab; correspondence on efforts to secure funds for joint Pitt-Brazil program; dumbwaiter in Thaw Hall; correspondence on Crystallography Lab.
- Cultural and Educational Exchange, 1958-1960 (Box 16, Folder 128)
  Mid-summer reports of year recipients of Summer Travel Study Awards, 1958-1959; correspondence and memos on exchange awards and special events, foreign students; correspondence on exchange relationship with Tsing Hua University; foreign science teacher program; roster of educational exchange personnel, 1959-1960; Pittsburgh Council for International Visitors.
- Cultural and Educational Exchange, 1960-1961 (Box 16, Folder 129)
  Foreign science teacher program and travel abroad.
- Cultural and Educational Exchange, 1961-1962 (Box 16, Folder 130)
- Cultural and Educational Exchange, 1962-1963 (Box 16, Folder 131)
  Foreign Science teacher program; fourth Bay College project; "Pitt Explores the World on WPGH"; list of students and faculty from abroad, 1962-1963.
- Cultural and Educational Exchange, 1963-1964 (Box 16, Folder 132)
  Enrollment from abroad, 1963-1964; "Interviews abroad 1964" publication in India; international seminars; travel abroad; memos.
- Cultural and Educational Exchange, 1964-1965 (Box 16, Folder 133)
  Enrollment from abroad, 1964-1965, and memos.
- Cultural and Educational Exchange, 1965-1967 (Box 17, Folder 134)
  Enrollment from abroad, 1965/1966-1966/1967; travel abroad; memos.
- Departments - Growth Chart (Box 17, Folder 135)
- Departments - Annual Reports, 1956-1962 (Box 17, Folder 136)
- Departments - Allegheny Observatory, Annual Reports, 1956-1962 (Box 17, Folder 137)
- Departments - Biological Sciences, Annual Reports, 1956-1962 (Box 17, Folder 138)
- Departments - Biophysics, Annual Reports, 1956-1962 (Box 17, Folder 139)
- Departments - Chemistry, Annual Reports, 1956-1962 (Box 17, Folder 140)
- Departments - Geology, Annual Reports, 1956-1962 (Box 17, Folder 141)
- Departments - Mathematics, Annual Reports, 1956-1962 (Box 18, Folder 142)
- Departments - Physics, Annual Reports and Sarah Mellon Scaife Radiation Laboratory, 1956-1962 (Box 18, Folder 143)
- Departments - Psychology, Annual Reports, 1956-1962 (Box 18, Folder 144)
- Departments - Chair Meetings, 1956-1958 (Box 18, Folder 145)
- Departments - Chairs, 1958-1960 (Box 18, Folder 145A)
  Department heads meeting agendas and minutes, 1950-1960; description of National Defense graduate fellowship program in Natural Sciences; working paper on pre-registration for trimester operations.
- Departments - Chairs, 1960-1962 (Box 18, Folder 146)
  Agendas and minutes of Department Head meetings with attachments on library acquisitions; memo on department problems.
- Departments - Chairs, 1962-1964 (Box 18, Folder 147)
  Department Head meeting agendas and minutes; memos on policies of graduate courses; submission of faculty names for 11th edition "American Men of Science."
- Departments - Chairs, 1964-1965 (Box 19, Folder 148)
  Department Head meeting agendas and minutes; "Flight from Teaching" summary of 1963/1964 annual report of Carnegie Foundation for advancement of teaching; memos on fund raising; papers on International Dimensions programs.
- Departments - Chairs, 1965-1968 (Box 19, Folder 149)
  Department Head meeting agendas and minutes; draft charter for proposed University Committee on programs and goals; memo on Spanish instruction; By- Laws of Board of Trustees; memo on non-tenured faculty; memo on graduate student assistant pay scale; memo on costs of new campus building projects; memo on organizational changes at University; full enrollments, Fall 1966/1967; correspondence on Pitt joining Association of Midwestern Universities; enrollment report; DNS highlights for Annual report; memo on need for natural scientist on Ecuador Project; memo on Board of Visitors; status report of Earth and Planetary Sciences, September 1, 1967.
- Departments - Questionnaire on Faculty, 1959-1960 (Box 19, Folder 150)
- Faculty Meeting Minutes, 1956-1959 (Box 19, Folder 151)
- Faculty Meeting Minutes, 1959-1963 (Box 20, Folder 152)
- Development, 1958-1960 (Box 20, Folder 153)
  Guest lists, Chancellor's luncheon with community leaders at Duquesne Club and Chancellor's football luncheons (Friends of the University); fiscal needs of Law School, 1959; financial development program for Academic Disciplines, 1960-1965; proposal for pre-doctoral fellowship in genetics and related fields, 1960; list of directors, Kettering Foundation.
- Development, 1960-1961 (Box 20, Folder 154)
  Legislative Day planning, 1960; "Economy of Giving" brochure; list of 5 universities and how they spent Ford Foundation money; list of prospective Pitt corporate donors; development plans for Academic Disciplines.
- Development, 1961-1963 (Box 20, Folder 155)
  Correspondence on donated used equipment; correspondence about Dr. Lauffer presenting Dr. Merriam Trytten with honorary degree at 175th anniversary convocation; news release on Chancellor's speech on Education as Growth Industry, January 29, 1963; Development plans for Academic Disciplines report, 1963.
- Development, 1963-1968 (Box 20, Folder 156)
  Pamphlet on Good Way for fundraising by Paul Davis; correspondence on donated equipment; correspondence with charitable funds; Vice Chancellor's memo on handling gifts in kind; "Renaissance" brochure; proposal on fund raising in Natural Sciences, 1967; summary of development fund requests, 1967.
- Development - Alumni Activities, 1958-1964 (Box 21, Folder 157)
- Development - Long Range Plans, 1959-1967 (Box 21, Folder 158)
  Correspondence on needs of all Natural Sciences departments, 1959; development projects in Division, 1966; program development funds needs of Academic Disciplines, 1966.
- Development - Ten-Year Plans, 1962-1963 (Box 21, Folder 159)
  Projected staff and equipment needs for Natural Sciences Departments.
- Development - Ten Year Plans, 1966-1967 (Box 21, Folder 160)
  Projected staff and equipment needs for Natural Sciences Department following state relatedness.
- Dewey Foundation for Study of Cycles, 1962-1965 (Box 21, Folder 161)
  Director's report explaining work of Foundation; report of comparative cycle study (individual phenomena in 5.9 year cycle and other year terms); proposal for international conference on cyclic phenomena, 1964.
- Disciplines, 1958-1960 (Box 21, Folder 162)
  Relationship between Academic Disciplines and School Liberal Arts; copy of speech by scholar-in-residence, Hayward Keniston; policy on travel funds, 1959; memo on integration of Division Natural Sciences with other schools and with University divisions; organization and interest of Academic Disciplines report, 1960; memo about reorganization of department of Modern Languages; minutes of staff meetings, 1959/1960.
- Disciplines, 1960-1962 (Box 21, Folder 163)
  Correspondence on prospective deans for Humanities; memo on lecture series in Chinese area center; minutes of staff meetings, 1950-1962; announcement about Thompson as acting Chairmen of Sociology, 1961/1962; correspondence about East Asian Studies; foreign languages with names of department chairmen and Italian 180 course; memo appointing Chinitz as Department Head of Economics; undergraduate program in Economics; list of courses taught by Mellon professors.
- Disciplines, 1962-1963 (Box 21, Folder 164)
  Brochures describing graduate study in each Natural Science Department; memo on Chancellor's retreat; announcement of Theatre productions; announcement of establishment of Department of East Asian Languages and Literature, January 4, 1963; minutes of staff meetings, 1962-1963; memo on prospective social sciences dean; university policy on discrimination.
- Disciplines, 1963-1965 (Box 21, Folder 165)
  Memo on Music Department's chamber orchestra; memo from Linguistics department on coordinating research; memo on prospective Social Sciences Dean; notice of space technology conference; memo on special subcommittee on chairmanship of Social Psychology; minutes of staff meetings, 1963-1965; correspondence on teaching; memo on cooperation with community colleges; correspondence on Soviet Studies; memos on linguistics; organizational chart, Academic disciplines; course changes in Anthropology; reorganization of Psychology Department.
- Disciplines, 1965-1966 (Box 22, Folder 166)
  Memo on proposed committee on instructional technology; proposal for joint religious studies program with Pittsburgh Theological Seminary; correspondence about Oakland Plan; memo on Social Psychology; agreements on funding Omar Moore's research projects; responsive environment; Moore's paper "Autotelic responsive environments and exceptional children," 1963; staff meeting minutes.
- Disciplines, 1966-1967 (Box 22, Folder 167)
  Statement of instruction responsibilities; position paper on Asian Studies; correspondence on instructional technology; correspondence on Dean Wadsworth paper about proposed social sciences building; search for Dean of Social Sciences.
- Disciplines - Professorships, 1958-1964 (Box 22, Folder 168)
  List of potential donors for endowed professorships; correspondence with Professor Bompiani, Rome, about Mellon Professorship; press clippings on first two Mellon appointments; recommendations for professorships; "Role of Academic Disciplines in a Modern University" address by Chancellor Litchfield about Mellon Grant for professor; list of Mellon professors and their lecture schedule, 1963/1964.
- History, 1958-1963 (Box 22, Folder 169)
  "Research History of Chemistry Department" by Alexander Silverman, 1945; letter describing University's academic divisions; History of Development of Research programs in Natural Sciences; History of Pymatuning Lab; History of Cyclotron funds; reports from each department as to how they handle internal communication, May 1961.
- 80-series Course Material, 1964-1965 (Box 22, Folder 170)
- 80-series Course Material, 1965-1966 (Box 22, Folder 171)
- Faculty Meetings, 1965-1966 (Box 22, Folder 172)
  Minutes; statement of faculty opinion on University future, August 4, 1965; statement on future from GSPIA faculty; comments on state relatedness by S. Rosenberg, November 9, 1965; notice of general faculty meeting; resolution on faculty participation in nominating Board of Trustees members; resolution of Natural Sciences Committee on Faculty-Trustee Communication; Statement of Educational Policies Committee to Board of Trustees, June 3, 1965; faculty vote on University calendar; classified research and modern language requirement; course offerings, Spring and Summer 1967.
- Faculty Meeting, November 3, 1966 (Box 23, Folder 173)
  Classified research survey from Natural Sciences departments; statement on research endorsed by Senate; correspondence on classified research; correspondence on language requirement; recommendations from Graduate faculty, Natural Sciences; list of universities' language requirements for graduate study; proposals for trimester calendar; minutes of faculty meeting.
- Joint Participation, 1960-1967 (Box 23, Folder 174)
  Carnegie Institute of Technology; interdisciplinary activities; School of Medicine; Mellon Institute; correspondence about relationships with other area educational institutions.
- Objectives, 1959-1965 (Box 23, Folder 175)
  Functions and objectives of DNS, 1959/1960; evaluations of DNS, Earth and Planetary Science, Biology, Mathematics, Chemistry, Physics, 1964/1965.
- Seminars, 1960 (Box 23, Folder 176)
- Science Development Plan, 1966-1967 (Box 23, Folder 177)
  Correspondence on the plan, 1966/1967; draft and final copy of University of Pittsburgh, Division of Natural Sciences, Science Development Plan, January 5, 1967.
- Draft Deferment, 1958-1961 (Box 23, Folder 178)
- Education, 1958-1967 (Box 23, Folder 179)
  Continuing education for alumni; invitations to attend education conference; science program for elementary education students; seminar in College Teaching; changes in teacher certification; "New Directions in Teacher Education: The Graduate Internship Program; a Five-Year Report 1960-65" by the School of Education, University of Pittsburgh, 1965; American Council on Education, 1958/1959-1964/1965.
- Education, School of, 1958-1967 (Box 23, Folder 180)
  Correspondence on Educational Placement Office, 1958-1959; training program for foreign teachers 1960-1961; certification requirements in Pennsylvania, 1963; correspondence on seminars and conferences; "A Statement Relating to Future Developments and Expanding Needs of the School of Education," 1960; academic course offerings for graduate students in education; guidelines for the preparation programs of teachers of secondary school science and mathematics; analysis of graduate courses offered in the academic discipline in departments of Mathematics, Chemistry, Physics, Biology, and Earth and Planetary Sciences, 1965/1966-1966/1967.
- Educational Resources and Services, 1962-1966 (Box 23, Folder 181)
  Correspondence about Committee on University Services; career counseling -educational enrichment for secondary schools; EDUCOM periodical, 1965/1966-1966/1967.
- Engineering and Mines, 1958-1963 (Box 23, Folder 182)
  Preliminary and final programs of ASEE annual meeting sponsored by University of Pittsburgh and C.I.T., 1959; correspondence on DNS courses for engineering students; survey of nuclear education programs; preparation of proposal to Ford Foundation; search for new dean of engineering.
- Engineering and Mines, 1963-1965 (Box 23, Folder 183)
  Inquiries from international students about entrance; proposals for the Industrial Engineering Ph.D.; correspondence about deanship search; Dr Harold E. Hollscher named dean as of July 1, 1965; ECPD inspection for re-evaluation.
- Engineering and Mines, 1965-1967 (Box 24, Folder 184)